<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Malice rebuked, or A character of Mr. Richard Baxters abilities. And a vindication oe [sic] the Honourable Sr. Henry Vane from his aspersions in his Key for Catholicks, as it was sent in a letter formerly to Mr. D.R. and is now printed for the publike satisfaction. / By Henry Stubbe of Ch. Ch. in Oxon.</title>
            <author>Stubbe, Henry, 1632-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1841_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209630</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868495</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94086)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 230:E1841[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Malice rebuked, or A character of Mr. Richard Baxters abilities. And a vindication oe [sic] the Honourable Sr. Henry Vane from his aspersions in his Key for Catholicks, as it was sent in a letter formerly to Mr. D.R. and is now printed for the publike satisfaction. / By Henry Stubbe of Ch. Ch. in Oxon.</title>
                  <author>Stubbe, Henry, 1632-1676.</author>
                  <author>Stubbe, Henry, 1632-1676. Vindication of that prudent and honourable knight, Sir Henry Vane, from the lyes and calumnies of Mr. Richard Baxter, minister of Kidderminster.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year MDCLIX. [1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The "vindication oe the honourable Sr. Henry Vane" is a reply to Baxter's "A key for Catholicks".</note>
                  <note>Apparently sometimes issued with Wing S6045: "An essay in defence of The Good old Cause.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vane, Henry, --  Sir, 1612?-1662 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Key for Catholicks --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170450:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MALICE REB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KED,</hi> OR A CHARACTER OF Mr. <hi>Richard Baxters</hi> ABILITIES. AND A VINDICATION OE THE Honourable Sr. HENRY VANE FROM HIS ASPERSIONS in his <hi>Key for Catholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was ſent in a Letter formerly to Mr. <hi>D.R.</hi> and is now printed for the publike Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By HENRY STUBBE of</hi> Ch. Ch. <hi>in</hi> Oxon.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 12.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The lip of truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever: but a lying tongue is but for a moment.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170450:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170450:2"/>
            <head>READER,</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Know many perſons will be apt to cenſure this enſuing piece, as being too <hi>virulent,</hi> conſidering the diſparity of <hi>years, repute,</hi> and that <hi>calling</hi> in which <hi>Mr. Baxter</hi> lives. I profeſſe I have no <hi>perſonall quarrell</hi> with the man, nor have I read more of his workes then I was neceſſitated unto for the penning of this letter: he ſhould ſtill have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed his <hi>ill-founded eſteem,</hi> if it had not been <hi>abuſed</hi> to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicy of the <hi>Good old cauſe,</hi> and the <hi>Common-wealths-men:</hi> I have followed an <hi>example</hi> of his own giving, and it were not fitting that <hi>Court-paraſites</hi> ſhould be wore
<pb facs="tcp:170450:3"/>
               <hi>forward</hi> and <hi>ſervent</hi> to <hi>enſlave</hi> us, then we to defend our Liberty. As I <hi>voluntarily</hi> engaged in a vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Honourable <hi>Sr. Henry Vane,</hi> ſo beſides the <hi>reſentments of Gratitude</hi> which I have for his many favours, I brought with me thoſe of a more <hi>generall concerne:</hi> and I make it my moſt humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to that <hi>Honourable perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,</hi> if I have fallen into any miſ-becoming tranſports in a diſcourſe wherein <hi>his name</hi> was mentioned, that he would not interpret my <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>ardour</hi> for the publique, as a <hi>diminiſhing</hi> of that <hi>reſpect</hi> which is due to him from <hi>me</hi> and <hi>all the VVorld.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170450:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Could wiſh the ſubject of this letter could yeeld you more divertiſement then the preſent poſture of our Affaires will permit, and that I might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain you with a <hi>pleaſing</hi> as well as <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> diſcourſe. The <hi>Age</hi> wherein <hi>we live</hi> hath been all Miracles; and the coming forth of the <hi>Woman</hi> out of the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> hath been attended with ſo many wonders, that a <hi>pious heart</hi> can never want Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in its contemplations. <hi>We</hi> have ſeen and our eyes bear witneſs to the Actings of our <hi>God,</hi> the overturning of a <hi>Monarchy</hi> ſetled upon the foundation and <hi>uſage</hi> of many hundreds of years, ſtrenthened by what <hi>humane policy</hi> could contribute to it's eſtabliſhments, and what of <hi>buttreſſe</hi> a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Clergy</hi> could aſſiſt it with, out of the <hi>Pulpit:</hi> yet have <hi>we</hi> ſeen a <hi>change</hi> ſo brought about by our <hi>Jehovah,</hi> that he may in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, acknowledgements be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, <hi>Wonderfull, Counſellour the mighty God, the Everlaſting Father, Prince of peace.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170450:4"/>We have ſeen the <hi>moſt glorious cauſe</hi> in the World accompanied with no leſſe <hi>ſucceſſe,</hi> and the Lord in his <hi>mercy</hi> to us, and <hi>juſtice</hi> to them, <hi>Hath bound our King in chaines, and Nobles in fetters of iron,</hi> ſuch as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they had formerly oppreſſed the <hi>good people</hi> of this land. <hi>This honour have all his Saints;</hi> (Pſ. 149. v. 9.) Vengeance hath he returned upon their heads, and their own ſhame hath covered them. The <hi>true anointed ones</hi> of the Lord have appeared, for <hi>their ſakes</hi> hath he <hi>rebuked Monarchs,</hi> and the <hi>former</hi> have reaped the fruits of that <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Sacriety,</hi> whereunto the <hi>latter</hi> vainly pretended. But Sr. to our no ſmall diſcouragement after ſuch expence of <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>treaſure,</hi> after ſuch high <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes</hi> and <hi>conteſts</hi> in the field, after ſo many <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>teares</hi> ſhed, and that we were in hopes to ſee our ſelves (in a literall ſenſe) no longer <hi>aliens from the Common-wealth of Iſrael,</hi> but enjoying thoſe <hi>Liberties, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,</hi> and <hi>Civill,</hi> into which the Lord had enfranchiſed us; that <hi>God</hi> who had ſecured us from the <hi>malice</hi> of our <hi>foes,</hi> and broken their violence, hath occaſioned our ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling by <hi>counterfeit friends;</hi> and <hi>falſe-hearted brethren</hi> have almoſt reduced us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Egypt,</hi> to the <hi>houſe of bondage,</hi> after all our endeavours for ſuch immunities, as, when we thought our ſelves <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> of them, we did not ſufficiently <hi>improve.</hi> Theſe things to a <hi>Cato,</hi> to a ſpirit acted onely by <hi>Gallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170450:4"/>would be inſupportable; and a <hi>Soul</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated onely with the concerns of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man</hi> in his <hi>grandeur,</hi> would not out live. But <hi>we have not ſo learned Chriſt:</hi> we know it is God's uſuall way to endear his favours to his children, by heightning their <hi>Expectation,</hi> and profering onely at firſt that wherein he will afterwards enſtate them. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> began to think <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>-wards <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> taskmaſters ſaid the <hi>people</hi> were <hi>idle,</hi> and thereupon they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their oppreſſions: when the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Engliſh</hi> put on thoughts of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and claimed their priviledges in <hi>Spirituall</hi> and <hi>Civill</hi> intereſts; it was objected that <hi>riches</hi> and <hi>eaſe</hi> had made them rebellious; our <hi>Parliaments</hi> became diſcontinued, the <hi>Court</hi> employed their utmoſt Artifices to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce a <hi>Vaſſallage:</hi> but after that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> had diſengaged us from thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances, and that we were upon our way to <hi>Freedom</hi> by the help and conduct not of one <hi>Moſes,</hi> but many <hi>illustrious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages,</hi> whoſe <hi>Memory</hi> ſhall live when that of <hi>Thraſybulus, Timoleon, Epaminondas, Brutus, Valerius</hi> or any worthies <hi>Greece</hi> or old <hi>Rome</hi> could ever boaſt of, ſhall <hi>ceaſe</hi> to be mentioned. When we were upon the way to <hi>freedom</hi> and <hi>happineſs,</hi> when we were within ſight of the <hi>Cape of good hope,</hi> after a perillous voyage thorough an <hi>Ocean</hi> of blood: then it befell us, as it did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> after they had caſt off <hi>Pharaoh's</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170450:5"/>yoake, and paſſed the <hi>red ſea</hi> under the protect on of God viſibly appearing in their behalf, the <hi>Spies</hi> brought an <hi>ill report</hi> upon the land, <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (men queſtionleſſe, of extraordinary Endowments, and <hi>pretenders to ſanctity</hi>) theſe created diviſions, <hi>Aaron</hi> together with <hi>Miriam</hi> murmured, and ſuch confuſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſundry occaſions aroſe, that what might have proved a journey of a <hi>few days,</hi> was protracted 40 Years, and thoſe men who had been inſtrumentall in bringing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and felt the comfort of the viſible preſence of God, and had eaten <hi>Monnah,</hi> all theſe <hi>loſt</hi> their <hi>workes</hi> (if not themſelves) and after much wandring and travaile <hi>two onely</hi> of them (though their <hi>children</hi> lived to enjoy what their <hi>Fathers</hi> had the <hi>promiſe</hi> of) entred into <hi>Canaan.</hi> Sr. Our caſe hath been parallell to thoſe accidents, and we may therein read the grounds of our Confidence, that thorough a <hi>reſemblance</hi> of events the <hi>ſame providence</hi> operateth now in us, which did of old, and we expect the <hi>ſame iſſue,</hi> though (I hope) ſo farre bettered, that a <hi>greater number</hi> ſhall enjoy the benefit of their firſt intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then did formerly in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Truly, I am nothing diſcouraged at thoſe emergencies, thoſe diſorders, and that loſſe which we are at; I aſſure my ſelf theſe are but the <hi>pangs</hi> of that <hi>birth</hi> in which we ſhall at laſt with joy cry out, <hi>A
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170450:5"/>man-child is born:</hi> and not the paines at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending a falſe conception, a dead of-ſpring, or ſuch as whereto there <hi>wants strength</hi> to <hi>bring forth.</hi> God will not <hi>looſe</hi> his <hi>own mercies,</hi> and all is but as the wandrig <hi>Jews</hi> in the <hi>deſert,</hi> or as the <hi>going back</hi> of the <hi>ſun</hi> upon the dyall of <hi>Ahaz</hi> ten degrees, which was a <hi>ſigne</hi> of <hi>recovery</hi> to diſconſolate and languiſhing <hi>Hezechiah.</hi> But though I am confident of the <hi>finall iſſue</hi> of things, that the <hi>priſoners of hope</hi> ſhall receive double ſatisfaction, and the <hi>ranſomed of the Lord ſhall return, and come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ion with ſongs, and everlaſting joy upon their heads; they ſhall obtain joy, and gladneſs, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away:</hi> However theſe may be my thoughts, yet I ſuppoſe I may juſtly be afflicted for the attempts of ſuch as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to reinſlave us. Shall I ſay onely, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſlave</hi> us, and put upon our necks the <hi>former yoake.</hi> No, Sr. we are not ſo little verſed in the World, as to ignore, that <hi>New Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments,</hi> though <hi>Good,</hi> create advantages <hi>for after-times,</hi> and not thoſe <hi>wherein they are erected;</hi> but ſuch as are <hi>bad</hi> threaten all with <hi>perpetuity</hi> of misfortunes, unleſſe <hi>God</hi> be more <hi>mercifull</hi> then <hi>man</hi> is <hi>wiſe.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions now are of that Nature, as if they ſhould bid us, not returne to <hi>Goſhen,</hi> but the moſt <hi>diſmall parts</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> rather then proceed on to our <hi>Felicity.</hi> Nay this is not all which my ſoul regrets (though to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede from <hi>Engagements, Remonſtrances, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170450:6"/>and <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> to <hi>forſake</hi> that <hi>providence</hi> to ſlight thoſe mercies which we implored with tears, be things meriting our higheſt reſentments, and the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences whereof may involve, not the <hi>Actours</hi> alone, but ſuch as <hi>afflict their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſouls</hi> for the ſins of <hi>Sodom;</hi> and they who are <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to their <hi>crimes participate</hi> often in the puniſhments of the wicked, as <hi>Elijah</hi> ſuffered by the famine, though <hi>Ahab and his Father's houſe troubled Iſrael</hi>) cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely we ought all to lay it to Heart, That the <hi>Ambitious</hi> ones of theſe times are not content to render others <hi>miſerable,</hi> (by depriving them of, or endangering them in their Liberties and fortunes) unleſſe they can make them <hi>criminall</hi> to: and ſince the <hi>integrity</hi> of our <hi>Patriots</hi> is ſo well <hi>known,</hi> that <hi>Envy</hi> it ſelf can faſten no <hi>real imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> upon them, they muſt be blemiſhed with <hi>ſurmiſes</hi> and imaginations, and what is <hi>defective</hi> in the <hi>proofe</hi> of the <hi>charge,</hi> the <hi>Authority</hi> of thoſe that divulge it, muſt ſupply. I could inſtance in many perſons of <hi>ſuch worth,</hi> that this Age may bluſh they are not in <hi>greater dignities,</hi> to which they would give a <hi>luſtre</hi> rather then receive any thence themſelves: (It was a <hi>complaint</hi> of the wiſe man, <hi>an evill under the ſun,</hi> and <hi>an errour,</hi> that <hi>folly ſhould be ſet in great digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the rich ſit in lowe place,</hi> that <hi>ſervants were upon horſes, and Princes walked as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants upon the Earth.</hi> How much more
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170450:6"/>ought we to be aggrieved to ſee the moſt <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>prudent</hi> counſellours outed, and diſgraced, and men of <hi>different qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> advanced?) yet theſe men are aſperſed and vilified thoroughout the Nation, and by an uncouth barbarity they are aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their reputes, and whoſe <hi>names</hi> ſhould be as <hi>pretious ointments powred forth,</hi> theſe are repreſented as <hi>ſuch</hi> which <hi>dead flies have infected with a ſtinking ſavour.</hi> But their <hi>implacable malice</hi> hath diſcovered it ſelf againſt no man ſo much, as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Sr. <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> one whom not to have <hi>heard</hi> of, is to be a <hi>ſtranger</hi> in this land; and not to <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>admire,</hi> is to be an <hi>Enemy</hi> to all that is <hi>good</hi> and <hi>vertuous:</hi> One, whoſe <hi>integrity,</hi> whoſe <hi>uprightneſs</hi> in the greateſt employments hath ſecured him from the effects of their Hatred, (veiled with juſtice) in whom his <hi>ſincere piety, Zeal for the publick,</hi> and <hi>ſingular wiſdom</hi> may have raiſed <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>dread.</hi> Againſt him have they ſet themſelves, him have they damnified in his Eſtate, prejudiced in his Liberty, and laboured to diſgrace unto the people of his native countrey; but finding the <hi>Court-artifices</hi> to fail, and that his <hi>inocence</hi> was not ſo to be prevailed upon, they have at length incenſed the Pulpit againſt him, and made uſe of Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter's</hi> pen to ſerve their ends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sr. Henry Vane</hi> publiſhed (in 1655) a book called, <hi>The retired mans meditations,</hi> in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170450:7"/>which he hath diſcovered the moſt glorious Truths that have been <hi>witneſſed</hi> unto theſe 1500 years and more, in a manner as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary. I mean not in the <hi>perſwaſive words</hi> of humane wiſdom, not in the <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry</hi> of School-learning, not as the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> but <hi>as one having Authority,</hi> and in the <hi>evidence</hi> and <hi>demonſtration of the Spirit:</hi> in that Booke (upon which none hitherto hath animadverted but Mr. <hi>Finch,</hi> who had never yet found a name in the World, but by the eſteem of his Adverſary) he hath layed down this poſition: That <q>
                  <hi>the Myſtery of iniquity working in men of a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall conſcience, is the Magiſtrates entermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Chriſts power over the judgments of men.</hi>
               </q> Upon which ſaying that may ſerve for a paraphraſe which is layed down by the ſame Author in his <hi>Healing Queſtion,</hi> where ſpeaking of <hi>freedom to be exerciſed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in matters of religion, or that concern the ſervice and worſhip of God,</hi> He ſaith, <q>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto this freedom the Nations of the World have right and title by the purchaſe of Chriſt's blood; who by vertue of his death and reſurrection is become the ſole Lord and ruler in and over the conſcience; for to this end Chriſt died, roſe, and revived, that he might be Lord both of the dead and living; and that every one may give an account of himſelf, in all matters of God's worſhip, unto God and Chriſt alone, as their own Master, unto whome they ſtand or fall in judgement, and are not in theſe things to be oppreſſed, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170450:7"/>brought before the judgement ſeats of men. For why ſhouldſt thou ſet at nought thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in matters of his Faith and conſcience, and herein intrude into the proper office of Chriſt, ſince we are all to ſtand before the judgement-ſeat of Christ, whither Governors or Governed, and by his deciſion onely are capable of being declared with certainty, to be in the right, or in the wrong?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>By <hi>vertue then of this ſupream law, ſealed and confirmed in the blood of Chriſt unto all men (whoſe ſoules he challenges a propriety in, to bring under his inward rule in the ſervice and worſhip of God) it is that all Magiſtrates are to fear and forbear inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling with giving rule or impoſing in thoſe matters. They are to content themſelves with what is plain in their commiſſion, as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God to be his Minister unto men for good, whileſt they approve themſelves the doers of that which is good in the ſight of men, and whereof earthly and Wordly judicatures are capable to make a clear and perfect judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which caſe the Magistrate is to be for praiſe and protection to them. In like manner he is to be a Miniſter of terrour and revenge to thoſe that doe evill in matters of outward practiſe, converſe, and dealings in the things of this life between man and man, for the cauſe whereof the judicatures of men are appointed and ſet up. But to exceed theſe limits, as it is not ſafe, nor warrantable for the Magistrate (in regard he who is higher
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170450:8"/>then the higheſt, regards, and will ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf diſpleaſed at it) ſo neither is it good for the people, who hereby are nouriſhed up in a biting, devouring, wrathfull ſpirit one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, and are found tranſgreſſors of of that Royall law which forbids us to doe that unto another, which we would not have them doe unto us, were we in their condition.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of Sr. H. V. might have been entertained with <hi>leſſe oppoſition,</hi> at leaſt <hi>rage,</hi> then it hath yet found in the ſpirits of many. I never reflect thereon, but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee <hi>Stephen praying</hi> for them that <hi>ſtoned</hi> him; and admire a <hi>Charity</hi> ſo <hi>diffuſive</hi> as not to compriſe onely <hi>friends</hi> but even <hi>enemies:</hi> a <hi>love</hi> beyond that of <hi>Publicans,</hi> towards them which <hi>hate, deſpitefully uſe,</hi> and <hi>perſecute:</hi> in fine, a <hi>perfection</hi> like that of our <hi>Heavenly Father,</hi> who (beſides that he <hi>makes</hi> them ſo) <hi>endureth with much long ſuffering the veſſells of wrath fitted for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> though he wont not <hi>power,</hi> though his <hi>knowledge</hi> by <hi>infallibly diſcerning,</hi> and his <hi>juſtice</hi> in <hi>puniſhing,</hi> both would be <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable:</hi> He <hi>knoweth who are his,</hi> yet doth he <hi>tolerate in</hi> [his] <hi>great houſe not only veſſels of Gold, and ſilver, but alſo of wood and earth, and ſome to honour, ſome to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter teacher of the Church at Kedermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter a Catholick Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and paſtour of a Church of ſuch at Keder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> Envoy from heaven,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170450:8"/>and <hi>Embaſſadour of Chriſt</hi> (as he calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Dedicat <hi>of Saints everlaſt. Reſt</hi>) he cannot endure this <hi>Tenet,</hi> this <hi>compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, tender</hi> and <hi>peaceable frame of ſpir it.</hi> From this <hi>Candid principle,</hi> and which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> the <hi>liberty</hi> of his <hi>ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> hath he taken an occaſion [in a late infamous Libell, if ſo great a <hi>farce</hi> may be ſo termed, called a <hi>Key for Catholiques</hi>] to decry the <hi>Vaniſts</hi> with ſuch language as may juſtly deſerve that reply of <hi>Michael</hi> to the <hi>devill,</hi> THE LORD REBUKE THEE. But, however this may be an <hi>Anſwer</hi> ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>Christian temper</hi> of Sr. H. V. and the <hi>quality of the perſon</hi> he hath to do with: yet becauſe ſeverall <hi>weake ones</hi> may be <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed</hi> into an <hi>ill opinion</hi> of that <hi>Honourable perſonage</hi> thorough that generall [though <hi>undue</hi>] eſteem which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>in the World</hi> for <hi>Learning, judgement</hi> and <hi>moderation,</hi> whereby <hi>innocence</hi> may be <hi>diſtreſſed</hi> and <hi>railing</hi> become <hi>hallowed;</hi> I ſhall vindicate Sr. H. V. from the reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this <hi>Philistim,</hi> or <hi>Shimei,</hi> or <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhakeh,</hi> and defend that <hi>invidious Aſſertion,</hi> but you muſt firſt give me leave to premiſe a <hi>character</hi> of the man, <hi>As the man is, ſo is his strength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot give you any account of the <hi>Birth</hi> or <hi>Education</hi> of Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> but I think I may ſay that he either <hi>never</hi> was at any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> or made <hi>little stay</hi> there, nor took any <hi>Degree;</hi> (unleſſe the late per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170450:9"/>of ſome may have prevailed with him, who apprehended ſomething of worth in him, and were ſenſible how great a detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might ariſe if <hi>Qualifications</hi> without <hi>univerſity degrees</hi> ſhould capacitate one for the <hi>Ministry</hi> in our days) in a Time when <hi>ignorance,</hi> or <hi>terrour,</hi> or <hi>both,</hi> had taken off the <hi>Ministers</hi> of this Nation from oppoſing thoſe called <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> then <hi>He</hi> tooke oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to <hi>ſignalize himſelf</hi> by an <hi>intricate Diſpute</hi> with honeſt Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> and the <hi>Act</hi> being <hi>plauſible</hi> the <hi>performance</hi> was thought <hi>great.</hi> Since that time he hath <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandized</hi> himſelf <hi>in the World,</hi> and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting not <hi>confidence</hi> to print what made for the <hi>interest of others,</hi> he knew <hi>he</hi> could not faile of the <hi>applauds</hi> of ſuch as (however they might diſcover his weakneſs) were <hi>concerned,</hi> nor of the <hi>reall admiration</hi> of ſuch as could not <hi>diſcerne.</hi> I am a <hi>stranger</hi> to his <hi>life,</hi> and report ſpeaks not much to his diſadvantage, nor is he <hi>wanting</hi> to his <hi>own praiſes.</hi> Whatever become of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>let not thy left hand know what thy right hand doth,</hi> he in <hi>ſeverall</hi> of his <hi>works</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainteth us with his <hi>charitableneſs</hi> to the <hi>poore,</hi> and his care for the <hi>ſick</hi> to whom he adminiſters <hi>Phyſick.</hi> Not that this <hi>ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of the Apostles, delegated by the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Anoints them with oyle, and ſo heales them:</hi> or cures them as he walks by vertue of his <hi>ſhadowe;</hi> nor doth he diſtribute <hi>hand-kerchiefes:</hi> but all (as I am told) is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170450:9"/>atchieved by <hi>looch ſanum</hi> and a <hi>liquoriſh ſtick,</hi> or <hi>Gaſcoines powder,</hi> &amp;c. Yea in his <hi>ſaints everlaſting reſt</hi> he is no leſſe tireſome with the recitall of his <hi>infirmities</hi> and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; then is <hi>Balzac</hi> or <hi>Voiture</hi> in their letters, with the <hi>Colick,</hi> and <hi>feavour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his <hi>learning</hi> the account he gives of himſelf is to have ſpent much time in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the <hi>Fathers,</hi> (of whoſe <hi>uſe</hi> or rather <hi>inutility</hi> read <hi>Daille</hi>) the <hi>Schoole-men</hi> (an upſtart ſtudy unknown to the purer times, modelled &amp; profeſſed by that Order which now manageth the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and was at firſt erected for the ſuppreſſing the truth in the <hi>Abbigenſes</hi> (and <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> ſuch as if the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had not <hi>Authoriſed</hi> us to call <hi>Vaine,</hi> their <hi>own writings</hi> would) How much he hath benefited in theſe ſtudies <hi>he</hi> hath endeavoured to give the World an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in a multitude of books, which he <hi>voides</hi> continually: <hi>Joachimus Fortius,</hi> who was reſolved to write <hi>a booke every yeere</hi> whileſt he lived, was but a <hi>ſlight pretender</hi> in compariſon to Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> works. And what <hi>Henry the fourth,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> ſaid of <hi>King James,</hi> that <hi>he was a fine King and wrote pretty little bookes:</hi> this makes up but a part of Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> commendations, he writes not onely <hi>ſingle ſheets,</hi> and <hi>little bookes,</hi> but <hi>large volumes.</hi> This <hi>tedious impertinent</hi> having run thorough the uſuall method of <hi>Engliſh</hi> controvertiſts, now aſſumes the faſhion of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and that our countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170450:10"/>may have ſomething of <hi>novelty</hi> in his papers, they who are in love with a <hi>lowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutch dreſſe,</hi> may have recourſe to Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters diſputations</hi> at <hi>Kederminſter:</hi> yea he out-goeth his pattern, for theirs are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes managed in <hi>vniverſities,</hi> but theſe <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminſterian diſputations</hi> have onely Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> for <hi>Preſident,</hi> Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> for <hi>reſpondent,</hi> Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> for <hi>Opponent:</hi> Thus I have ſeen ſome play at <hi>ſhittle-cock</hi> managing their <hi>battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doores</hi> in their <hi>right</hi> and <hi>left</hi> hands: Thus children play by themſelves at <hi>Cards:</hi> thus the mad-man in <hi>Horace</hi> imagined himſelf at the <hi>Roman ſports, in vacuo ſeſſor plauſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Theatro.</hi> But for ſuch as admire the man and buy his books, for whoſe ſakes the <hi>price</hi> is printed on the <hi>title-page,</hi> or at the <hi>end,</hi> at three farthings a ſheet; though that rate be not extraordinary for <hi>one</hi> or <hi>two</hi> books, yet they had need of faire eſtates that are in a poſſbility of buying according to the Quotient in the Revelations, <hi>Ten thouſand times ten thouſand, and thouſands of thouſands of ſheets.</hi> God Almighty thought it ſufficient to give us <hi>one booke,</hi> (if I may ſo call it) and that ſuch as <hi>to make the man of God perfect, thoroughly furniſhed to all good works:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> affordes us <hi>more,</hi> not <hi>furniſhing men to all good works,</hi> (unleſſe <hi>railing</hi> and <hi>uncharitableneſs</hi> doe that) and of that value, that one may <hi>cheaper</hi> buy the <hi>Bible</hi> that TRVE SAINTS EVERLASTING REST, then Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170450:10"/>FALSE one. He one told us, That, <q>
                  <hi>he judged thoſe Tostatus's impudently proud, who think the World ſhould read no bodie's works but theirs:</hi> yet for ought I can ſee <hi>Toſtatus</hi> will be but a <hi>puny ſcribler</hi> to him.</q> It was a pretty peice of <hi>Drollery</hi> in our <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious Romanciſt,</hi> to deſire Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his <hi>Saints everlasting rest,</hi> which he miſtakeing for a <hi>complement,</hi> poſſibly upon <hi>that ground</hi> may have created the <hi>Saints</hi> (that have <hi>leiſure-time</hi> from the <hi>ſincere word of God,</hi> and <hi>hours</hi> for which they are not <hi>accountable</hi>) more <hi>trouble.</hi> His works are ſtuffed with <hi>Citations</hi> and <hi>ſchool-notions</hi> and <hi>unſetling debates,</hi> yet he cannot but know, that the <hi>Judicious</hi> hold no part of <hi>Theology,</hi> or <hi>ſcholaſticall deductions</hi> to be matter of <hi>faith:</hi> which Aſſertion if it were as <hi>candidly</hi> owned amongſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as it is <hi>ingenuouſly</hi> profeſſed amongſt <hi>Papists,</hi> our <hi>faith-confeſſions</hi> would be much <hi>ſhorter,</hi> and the number of <hi>Heraſies</hi> without a <hi>perſecution</hi> ſoone abate Whither he hath read all the books he quoteth, I know not, but the <hi>falſe names of Authors</hi> (not recorded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>errata</hi>) makes his dealing <hi>ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious.</hi> In his <hi>Metaphyſicks</hi> he hath ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, that he hath incurred manifold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes thereupon, as (for example) he hath been charged with <hi>high blaſphemy</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>immanent Acts of God:</hi> from which <hi>tenet common reaſon</hi> would have acquitted him; as <hi>ordinary skill</hi> in <hi>reall philoſophy</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170450:11"/>would have ſhewed him the <hi>ridiculouſneſs</hi> and falſity of his <hi>ſimile</hi> of the <hi>Looking-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> I cannot inſiſt long upon theſe things, it being not my deſign to Catalogue Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> errours, but to give you a <hi>ſample</hi> of his proficiency in thoſe courſes he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: and oblige my <hi>credit</hi> unto you, that I ſhall upon any warning furniſh you with ſuch an <hi>after-reckoning,</hi> as will make good my opinion of him. As for <hi>Church-Herory</hi> I ſhall by and by tell you that he underſtands not <hi>Greeke,</hi> and ſo is not likely to have any <hi>perfection</hi> or <hi>aſſurance</hi> in that, or <hi>Chronology:</hi> judge of his skill however therein by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming againſt <hi>democraticall Government,</hi> which notwithſtanding was the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Christian aſſemblies</hi> till the people were deprived of their <hi>votes:</hi> and which was the Government of <hi>Iſrael</hi> inſtituted by <hi>God himſelf,</hi> beſides, in his <hi>Key,</hi> &amp;c. p. 330. he maketh the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> to <hi>ſpawn</hi> the doctrine of <hi>Liberty of conſcience;</hi> which is as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, as that <hi>Serarius</hi> call'd <hi>Herod</hi> a <hi>Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avellian: I</hi> ſhall have occaſion elſewere to ſhew how it is the doctrine of primitive Chriſtians: now let it ſuffice that <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> H. Vane</hi> is not more full in his judgment then <hi>Constantine the great,</hi> nor doth he inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any <hi>other practiſe</hi> then what was the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> and <hi>uſage</hi> of that <hi>Emperour.</hi> If <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> had not written in <hi>Greek</hi> I ſhould referre Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> to him in his life of <hi>Constantine</hi> lib. 2. c. 5.59. The <hi>Heathens</hi> had in his time their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170450:11"/>
               <hi>expenſes of publick ſacrifices</hi> defrayed out of the <hi>treaſury,</hi> and their <hi>Temples</hi> [though not all, yet moſt] <hi>openly</hi> were <hi>frequented;</hi> their <hi>Sophiſters</hi> were <hi>maintained</hi> by the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick purſe:</hi> they were employed in places of truſt, and dignity; <hi>civill</hi> and <hi>military:</hi> and all this not onely in the time of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> but even till <hi>Juſtinian's</hi> time in great part, as <hi>Procopius</hi> in his <hi>ſecret history</hi> tells us. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> did indeed refuſe to <hi>defray</hi> the ſacrifices of the <hi>Heathens</hi> out of the publick treaſury, yet even in his time the <hi>Senate</hi> were generally <hi>pagans,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the time of <hi>Gratian</hi> (if not after) it was the cuſtom of the <hi>Flamines</hi> or <hi>Heathen Priests</hi> to preſent the new <hi>Emperour</hi> (though <hi>Chriſtian</hi>) with a <hi>Stole</hi> or <hi>Pontificall garment,</hi> ſo that they had not onely a <hi>toleration,</hi> free and open, but even the <hi>Emperours</hi> were <hi>Chriſtian Emperours,</hi> but <hi>Heathen Priests.</hi> Thus you ſee, what others think would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce <hi>Heatheniſme,</hi> this was the courſe that brought in and eſtabliſhed <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> But theſe things being to be fetched out of <hi>Greek</hi> authours, I forgive Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance thereof, and onely tell him that the <hi>great ſouldier and eminent proteſtant Monſieur La Nove</hi> was of no other judgment then Sr. H. V. as one may read in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes; and that <hi>Poſſevin</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> wrote againſt him for it.</p>
            <p>As for his skill in <hi>languages</hi> it is ſo mean that I am amazed to ſee him quoted by the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170450:12"/>name of <hi>learned.</hi> The <hi>Syriack,</hi> the <hi>Arabick,</hi> both which are of great uſe for underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Scripture</hi> (of which you may read in Mr. <hi>Beveridge's</hi> diſcourſe of the Eaſtern tongues) upon the vulgar <hi>Analyſis</hi> of faith, of theſe I may ſuppoſe him <hi>totally</hi> ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. His skill in <hi>Hebrew</hi> is <hi>as little:</hi> Mr. <hi>Robertſon</hi> hath ſaid ſo much upon this ſubject in a particular book, that I ſhall not urge it: onely tell you that <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three days</hi> ſtudy in that tongue would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented ſome of his miſtakes; and <hi>one moneths</hi> diligence would have corrected ſuch <hi>lapſes</hi> as are not to be <hi>excuſed,</hi> or <hi>endured.</hi> Dare he <hi>boaſt</hi> unto the World, what time he hath ſpent in <hi>impertinencies,</hi> and yet be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of that which is almoſt the <hi>unum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium</hi> in his function! There is not that <hi>Quaker,</hi> or moſt <hi>fanaticall ſectarian</hi> (whom he ſo undervalues) but can ground his <hi>truthes</hi> upon the <hi>true verſion,</hi> and his <hi>errours</hi> upon the <hi>mistakes</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh tranſlatours.</hi> Of this you will be much more convinced, when I ſhall aſcertain you he is no better at <hi>Greeke</hi> then other tongues; weigh him in any <hi>ballance</hi> and you will finde him <hi>light.</hi> I ſhall not run over all his works, but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacque the moſt renowned <hi>Olio</hi> of <hi>practicall</hi> and <hi>Schoole-Divinity</hi> (the latter of which is apt to create <hi>everlaſting diſputes</hi> rather then <hi>rest:</hi> and made no part of the <hi>rest</hi> of the <hi>primitive,</hi> whither <hi>Chriſtians</hi> or <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians</hi>) I meane his <hi>Saints everlaſting reſt.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170450:12"/>In this book I obſerve he cites other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours at large in their originall <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but with the <hi>Greeks</hi> he deals not ſo. <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Clemens Alexandrinus, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, Laertius,</hi> theſe are cited either in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> or <hi>Latine.</hi> A man ſo <hi>ambitious</hi> to ſtuff his <hi>Margin,</hi> cannot be thought to have <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined</hi> this out of <hi>modeſty,</hi> which he <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>have done</hi> out of <hi>neceſſity,</hi> ſince in <hi>rationall</hi> diſcourſes other proofs are not allowed then which are fetched out of the tongue in which the Authour wrote. To evince this more, he hath adventured ſometimes to checquer his booke with <hi>Marginall</hi> Greeke words, though but ſeldome, as p. 74. there are placed two <hi>Greek</hi> words out of <hi>Polycarp,</hi> to no purpoſe that I can imagine, but to let men ſee Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of <hi>Greeke;</hi> p. 118. There ſtands a Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with an animadverſion that <hi>women ſhall not riſe again in their own Sex,</hi> which is a thing <hi>improbable,</hi> I would ſay <hi>falſe,</hi> if all the <hi>philoſophy</hi> I have, together with colourable texts of Scripture were a ground for ſuch peremptorineſs. p. 551. you have Greeke quoted out of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> but it is onely to diſgrace <hi>our Army,</hi> viz. that <hi>ſouldiers are Leopards,</hi> and <hi>the more they are favoured and regarded, the worſe.</hi> But he hath ſo beſpatter'd the <hi>Army</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly in his <hi>Key,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Key for Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, p. 319.</note> that I may forgive him this reflection, but I hope they will not pardon him that: ſo much lying and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170450:13"/>deſerves to be taken notice of, and they who have reſented, the diſgraces thrown upon the famous <hi>long Parliament;</hi> they who have avowed the puniſhment of the late <hi>King</hi> to have been condigne; they who have complained of <hi>catalogues</hi> being ſcatter'd abroad of ſuch as tried him, they in juſtice ought to demand exemplary ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction from Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> who hath dealt with them more bitterly and undeſervedly, then all the virulent pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets put together, which have come out fine theſe wars. But to proceed? p. 105. there Mr. Br. makes ſome ſhew of learning in a paſſage out of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> which too was not greatly materiall to any buſineſs he was then upon, but yet had ſomething of <hi>Novelty</hi> in it according to Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> judgment. Viz. that <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſhould call his <q>
                  <hi>condemnation to Martyrdome</hi> the DAMNA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION of the devill, <hi>becauſe his judges were but the Devills mouth and inſtruments.</hi> Fire, the Croſſe, cutting off, ſeparating, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my bones, rending of my members, deſtruction of my whole body, and the damnation of the Devil (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) let them all come upon me, ſo I but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to obtain Chriſt.</q> Ignar. ep. ad. Rom. p. 86. edit. Uſſer. Indeed Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> will find that he hath receded very much in this text from the minde of <hi>Ignatius:</hi> he might have excuſed himſelf by the <hi>Latin verſion</hi> which he follows, but that the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170450:13"/>of the <hi>Greeke</hi> deprives him of that excuſe. The words are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is pretty how Mr. Br. was put to it in this ſentence, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is interpreted in the lattin <hi>belluarum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia;</hi> out of this Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> could not frame any meaning and therefore omitted it in his Engliſh: it ſignifies either a <hi>collection of wilde beasts</hi> for the devouring men, as the <hi>Roman</hi> cuſtom was; or a <hi>letting them looſe to fight over the prey;</hi> and ſo alludes to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ancients, or <hi>fighting with beasts;</hi> to which malefactours, and ſeverall <hi>Martyrs</hi> were condemned. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe are not well rendred cutting off, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating: but the Latine had it, <hi>Abſciſſio, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratio:</hi> the former ſignifies a <hi>cutting up by beginning from the bottom of the belly:</hi> (as <hi>Eustathius</hi> ſomewhere expounds the word) and the later ſignifies a <hi>cutting in two,</hi> or <hi>in the middle;</hi> as the prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is ſaid to have been <hi>ſawed in two.</hi> So <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not <hi>breaking the bones,</hi> but the Latine had <hi>confractio oſſium,</hi> it was the <hi>ſcattering of the bones</hi> (or aſhes thereof) after that the <hi>body</hi> had been <hi>devoured</hi> or <hi>burned.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not the <hi>deſtruction of the body,</hi> but it was in his tranſlation <hi>interitus totius cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris.</hi> It ſignifies nothing but onely a <hi>reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs jactation,</hi> or <hi>inquietude of the body when one tumbles and toſſes.</hi> The word is an uſuall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170450:14"/>medicinall term, and Mr. Br. ſhould not be ſo little read in <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> as not to know the meaning of it,
<note place="margin">It is an Alluſion to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. where <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> obſerves it to be taken <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively</hi> not <hi>actively.</hi>
               </note> and that one might be under ſuch a <hi>reſtleſneſſe</hi> without the <hi>deſtruction of the body.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is not the <hi>damnation</hi> but <hi>puniſhment of the devill,</hi> viz. <hi>anguiſh of mind,</hi> or <hi>ejectment out of Heaven:</hi> but his tranſlatour deceived him, there he found <hi>damnatio diaboli.</hi> As for that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it ſignifies only <hi>that I may gain Christ,</hi> not <hi>that I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to obtain him:</hi> but he read in the ſame place, ut <hi>Chriſtum merear adipiſci.</hi> In ſum, upon peruſall of the place I find no induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment why I ſhould put Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation upon <hi>Ignatius:</hi> he expreſſes in moſt paſſionate terms his love and Zeal for Chriſt, and his defire to be with him: he wiſhes to be, <hi>devoured by beaſts,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth he is ready upon occaſion to force them to tear him: then addes, <q>
                  <hi>let me be conſumed with fire,</hi> crucified, <hi>torne by wilde beaſts, ſlaſhed or cut in pieces,</hi> let <hi>my bones be ſcatterd abroad:</hi> [theſe were puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments uſually inflicted upon malefactours and Martyrs]</q> 
               <hi>let my limbs be ſeizſed with aches</hi> [for I think <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the ſame with what phyſicians call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but he having uſed the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> before, did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline that phraſe afterwards] <hi>let a reſtleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe poſſeſs my whole body,</hi> [theſe are not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170450:14"/>effects of extrinſick violence in puniſhing, but of corporall indiſpoſition] <hi>and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the devill</hi> [this refers to afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mind] <hi>let all this come upon me ſo I may gain Chriſt,</hi> This is all he ſays, and neither in what precedes, or follows, does he leave any ground for Mr. <hi>Br's.</hi> aſſertion, that <hi>Ignatius</hi> calls his <hi>condemnation to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom</hi> the <hi>Damnation of the Devill, his judges being the Devills mouth and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> For ſuch his opinion I find no proof, but the deceit of a fraudulent interpreter, to whom if he had remitted us, all theſe errours (of ſo many in ſo little a compaſs you ſhall hardly find a man guilty of, though of never ſo mean parts) had not been imputed to his ignorance, which yet no leſſe diſcovers it ſelf (and with more danger to his <hi>Auditours</hi> and <hi>readers</hi>) in his ſcripturall interpretations: I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in one or two, that you may ſee however he may not in his <hi>devotions ſerve an unknown God,</hi> yet in his diſputes he ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth an <hi>unknown word of God,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertſon</hi> obſerved in his <hi>Old-teſtament</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes. In his <hi>ſecond ſheet</hi> for the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> he urgeth for the perpetuity of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall office (which, if I had leiſure, I would evidently ſhew how he hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown it) Matth. 28. v. 20. <hi>loe I am with you alway, even to the end of the World</hi> This text ſeems indifferently clear (in Engliſh) and to give ground to Mr <hi>Baxter's</hi> inſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170450:15"/>viz. <q>To this EXPRESSE promiſe <hi>Clem. Writer</hi> had no WISER an anſwer, but that <hi>[it is conditionall; if they teach all things that Chriſt hath commanded them, then he will be with them elſe not]</hi> Repl. This is your FORGERY: here is no ſuch words, but an ABSOLUTE promiſe. His being with them is to ſupport and help them in their work; and will you feign Chriſt to promiſe them help on conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they do it without?</q> But notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this confidence of Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> there is <hi>not any ſuch thing</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> as he lays down, and the <hi>London Miniſters.</hi> And in the ſecond place <hi>Clem. Writer's</hi> anſwer participates neither of that folly, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, with which Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> preſſeth him. It is evident, that <hi>Chriſt ſpake</hi> to his <hi>eleven diſciples onely:</hi> that he intended any more, cannot be proved, or ſaid without addition to the written word: Nay, ſince that Commiſſion is admitted by the <hi>Harmoniſts</hi> to be the ſame with that in Mark 16. v. 15. It is certainly perſonall, ſince thoſe that are to be converted by the preaching of thoſe commiſſioners to whom Chriſt ſpake, and to believe, ſeverall <hi>ſignes were to follow them,</hi> which <hi>are not</hi> now, nor <hi>have been</hi> theſe <hi>many years</hi> viſible. Furthermore, The text ſaith not, I <hi>am with you alway, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of the World.</hi> But either, <hi>Behold I am with you all the days</hi> [or time] <hi>untill the end of this Age</hi> Or, <hi>I am with you all</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170450:15"/>[your] <hi>days untill the end of</hi> [your] <hi>life.</hi> Upon any occaſion but this, which is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of intereſt, the words <hi>[for ever]</hi> (though it be a paſſage onely of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh verſion] ſhould have been interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſubject ſpoken of; as where it is ſaid, the ſervant, whoſe ear was bored, ſhould ſerve for ever. Exod. 21.6. Deut. 15.17. I have not ſeen any divine argue thence (as Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> doth here) that he ſhould live for ever, or that he muſt needs have ſucceſſours to verifie ſo EXPRESSE and abſolute a command: but that <hi>as long as he lived ſo long he ſhould ſerve;</hi> which is a man's <hi>for ever.</hi> The word in the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint</hi> there, is the ſame that here, and I could inform Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Scripture [<hi>Ezech.</hi> 26.] ſtands onely for the term of 70. years; and in other writers commonly for 100. or 110, as correſponding to the latin, <hi>Seculum.</hi> If any ſhall object that the text doth not contain the words [your days] nor <hi>end</hi> of [your] <hi>life.</hi> I anſwer, that it is uſuall for <hi>Divines</hi> interpreting Scripture to repeat ſuch pronounces <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as they call it, or from the paſſages fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going or ſubſequent in the ſame ſentence: I could inſtance in ſundry places, but I will give you a <hi>parallell</hi> one out of the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint.</hi> Deuter. 6. v. 24. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Sr. you may judge of this expoſition, and ſee how much more <hi>facile</hi> and <hi>naturall</hi> it is to <hi>repeat</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170450:16"/>then to inſert [your ſucceſſours] I ſhall now come to that which I firſt alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, viz. I <hi>am with you all the time untill the end of this age.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I will not begge the leaſt addition or gloſſe to make out this: read it without a comma after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the article <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> cannot be juſtly denyed to be <hi>Emphaticall</hi> and determine the promiſe (ſo expreſſe! ſo abſolute!) to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is again reſtrained by the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now I would fain know, ſince ſuch articles are in the <hi>writing,</hi> and <hi>Sermons</hi> of <hi>divines</hi> ſo often made <hi>Emphaticall,</hi> why I may not be allowed to make it ſo here? Is there <hi>a ballance and a ballance?</hi> God hates that. Shall we have different <hi>weights</hi> and <hi>meaſures,</hi> one for the <hi>commonalty,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the <hi>Sanctuary.</hi> If you read it with a <hi>comma</hi> after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the latter words art <hi>exegeticall,</hi> and (after the accuſtomed dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the Scripture) explain the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Give me leave to digreſſe a little in way of illuſtrating this interpretation. <hi>Chriſt</hi> being to depart, gives his Apoſtles their <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and telleth them what they muſt doe: They muſt <hi>teach all nations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>go into all the World</hi> (Marc. 16. <hi>v.</hi> 15.) and <hi>ſhould be witneſſes to him both in Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria and Jeruſalem, and all Judea, and unto the uttermoſt parts of the earth.</hi> This was a great work, and incumbred with many difficulties; perſecution, Scoffs, yea death
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170450:16"/>it ſelf was likely to be their portion. He had told them (Math. 24.) what was to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede upon their preaching, that he came not to ſend <hi>peace,</hi> but a <hi>ſword,</hi> that they ſhould be hated by them without, betrayed by them within, oppoſed by falſe Chriſts, finally, that they ſhould fall under ſo <hi>great</hi> a <hi>tribulation, as had not happened from the beginning of the World to that time, nor ever ſhould be again</hi> Math, 24.21. Marc. 13.19. Luc. 21.22. &amp;c. And this Anſwer he had given them upon an occaſionall queſtion Math. 24. v. 3. The diſciples asked him privately, Maſter <hi>what ſhall be the ſigne of thy coming,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>and of the end of the World?</hi> The words are the <hi>ſame</hi> with thoſe <hi>now</hi> controverted: and you may in the ch. 24. read an anſwer to that query, what is, as well as <hi>what ſhall be the ſignes of the end of the World?</hi> I ſhall not ſtay to prove that <hi>Chriſts</hi> anſwer is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the <hi>destruction of Jeruſalem,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of the <hi>Jewiſh polity, Janſenius</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> have done that for me. In the recitall of theſe <hi>afflictions</hi> he foretells them, we find frequent mention of the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation</hi> (as the <hi>vulgar</hi> calls it) or <hi>End.</hi> Math. 24. v. 6. <hi>but the end is not yet.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. he might have ſaid (and it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the <hi>queſtion</hi> that he meant) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And v. 14. <hi>then ſhall the end come</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In the <hi>Syriack</hi> (which language our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſpake in) not onely
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170450:17"/>(as in the <hi>Greeke</hi>) is there the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon expreſſion for the <hi>end of the World,</hi> but where the <hi>Greeke</hi> differenceth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that language</hi> doth not. It is ſaid alſo (and there is the like alluſion in the <hi>Syriack</hi>) that, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. Matth. 10.23. <hi>ye ſhall not have gone over</hi> [or <hi>finiſhed] all the cities of Iſrael till the ſon of man be come.</hi> It is true in this laſt place, he ſends them out <hi>onely</hi> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but his prediction of their being <hi>perſecuted</hi> ſo <hi>ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> agrees with his iterated <hi>prophecy,</hi> Matth. 24. we <hi>neither</hi> read that they were <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> in that <hi>voyage,</hi> nor doe we find that <hi>Chriſt came to them,</hi> but <hi>they to Chriſt.</hi> From theſe conſiderations, I ſuppoſe that the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> who had heard of what was like to be their <hi>lot</hi> and <hi>portion</hi> when the <hi>bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom</hi> ſhould be <hi>taken away:</hi> theſe children of the <hi>bridegroom</hi> (being not <hi>over-confident</hi> in Chriſt's promiſes, nor <hi>over-well-skilled</hi> in goſpell-myſteries; as he that reads the paſſages after <hi>Christ's reſurrection,</hi> and the <hi>question</hi> they propoſed to him at his <hi>aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Act. 1.6. may eaſily judge) might be ſorrowfull and troubled, as they had been at the diſcourſes made in <hi>John,</hi> being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to his <hi>departure,</hi> and withall, it is probable, that they might weigh <hi>their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,</hi> the <hi>greatneſs of the work,</hi> and the <hi>difficulties</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> attending, it which [to humane appearance] were likely to be <hi>greater</hi> then they could go thorough with,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170450:17"/>and bear up againſt for the <hi>firſt generation,</hi> when all would <hi>strive</hi> (and the <hi>attempt</hi> would be <hi>eaſie</hi>) to ſuppreſſe the <hi>growing ſect,</hi> whileſt it was in it's <hi>infancy.</hi> And upon this account Chriſt bidding them go out to preach (which act could not but renew the memory of former prediction) he addes for their comfort, and to prevent <hi>Objections, And behold I am with you to the end of the World.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. He who knew what was in the Heart of man, he anticipates all their objections and feares; The great <q>difficulty is in removing the ſetled law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and firſt eſtabliſhment of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: after the goſpel is once prevalent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver men, and that <hi>Moſes's</hi> preſcripts ſhall have vaniſhed before the <hi>Antitype,</hi> then indeed my preſence would not be ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as at the beginning; why? I came to this end that I ſhould by fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboliſh the <hi>Leviticall law,</hi>
               </q> and I will <hi>extraordinarily</hi> be with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> untill this <hi>generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> this preſent <hi>age,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s he told them that the <hi>greateſt perſecution that ever could happen,</hi> was then to be; ſo that it was neceſſary to promiſe an <hi>uncommon ſtrength</hi> for an <hi>unwonted tryal.</hi>
               </note> and poſture of affaires have an <hi>end</hi> or <hi>period.</hi> What is there in all this more then is commonly ſaid that <hi>miracles</hi> and an <hi>extraordinary preſence</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> was neceſſary for the <hi>planting,</hi> but not <hi>continuing</hi> of the <hi>Church?</hi> And is it not further ſaid <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.26. that Chriſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170450:18"/>came <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the end of the World,</hi> which <hi>end of the World</hi> is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the deſtruction of the <hi>Moſaicall</hi> laws and rites, which was not done till the ſubverſion of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> then <hi>Shilo</hi> came and the <hi>ſcepter</hi> departed from <hi>Judah:</hi> The <hi>old World</hi> or time <hi>before the law,</hi> and that other <hi>under the law,</hi> were the <hi>Worlds</hi> in the finiſhing of which Chriſt appeared. And you may further think, whether the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth not inply this in that he faith to the Corinthians (1 Cor. 10.11) <hi>theſe things were written for our admonition upon whom the ends of the World are come</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This <hi>diſconſolateneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> gave Chriſt occaſion to name the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> the <hi>Comforter:</hi> and [for the firſt age of the Church] he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to be <hi>with them</hi> (John. 14. v. 18.) and ſo to continue with them in a ſpeciall manner raiſing them up others beſides, <hi>ſome prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome paſtours and teachers</hi> (not that they ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> continue in a <hi>ſucceſſive ministry,</hi> but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Saints might be fitted</hi> for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Church, and <hi>building up the body of Chriſt.</hi> Which is not onely the reaſon of <hi>Miſſion,</hi> Rom. 10.15. (where to <hi>preach without ſending</hi> is repreſented not as <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> but as <hi>impoſſible;</hi> as <hi>impoſſible</hi> as to <hi>heare without preaching,</hi> or <hi>calling upon one of whom they have not heard.</hi>) which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary onely <hi>at first,</hi> and not to <hi>after-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcants;</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170450:18"/>but is the plain meaning of Epheſ. 4. v. 11, 12 as I ſhall ſhew you, after I have ſhewed more fully Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> ignorance in <hi>Scripture-diſputes,</hi> by his exception againſt <hi>Clem. Writer.</hi> What <hi>Clem. Writer</hi> objected is not <hi>forgery:</hi> How <hi>expreſſe</hi> and <hi>abſolute</hi> ſoever the <hi>promiſe</hi> be, yet often <hi>in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> ſuch denunciations are to be <hi>limited.</hi> Is the <hi>ſaying</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> more <hi>expreſſe</hi> then that of <hi>Jonah,</hi> Yet 40. <hi>dayes and Niniveh ſhall be deſtroyed?</hi> Viz. <hi>if</hi> they perſevere in their wickedneſs. They who were in the ſhip with <hi>Paul</hi> had an <hi>abſolute</hi> promiſe of their ſafety, Act. 27. v. 22.24. yet that was but <hi>conditionally</hi> to be underſtood. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept theſe</hi> [ſhipmen] <hi>abide in the ſhip, you cannot be ſaved v.</hi> 31. God <hi>ſware</hi> he would bring the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> into <hi>Canaan ſc. if</hi> they obeyed his voice, and murmured not. Numb. 14. v. 30. <hi>Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ye ſhall not come into the land concerning which</hi> I ſware <hi>to make you dwell therein.</hi> And to inſtance more particularly, the prophet tells <hi>Gehezi</hi> that the leproſie of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> ſhould cleave <hi>to him,</hi> and <hi>to his iſſue for-ever,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay the Septuagint. Yet hence it <hi>canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> be infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that <hi>Gehezi</hi> and his poſterity ſhould live <hi>for ever,</hi> or his ofspring ſhould <hi>never fail:</hi> but that as long as he, or any of his poſterity ſhould <hi>continue to live, ſo long</hi> they ſhould be leprous. Again, what <hi>Clem. Writer</hi> ſaid was not <hi>meer folly,</hi> for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170450:19"/>can any <hi>conſidering man</hi> deny, but in a <hi>Scripture-dialect, Go, teach all nations</hi> &amp;c <hi>teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I have commanded you; And lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the World:</hi> this may paſſe for <hi>Conditionall?</hi> Is it not allowable in common talke, <hi>Go, do this, or that,</hi> and <hi>lo I give you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now come to explain Epheſ. 4.11, 12. in which place I find Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to be the <hi>ſame man</hi> ſtill: and no better a <hi>textuary</hi> in one place then another. As in <hi>Matthew</hi> Chriſt promiſed the <hi>diſciples</hi> he would be <hi>with them</hi> till the totall remove of the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ordinances,</hi> and eſtabliſhment of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity;</hi> ſo the <hi>Apostle</hi> Epheſ. 4. ſaith that he made good his word; <hi>when he aſcended</hi> (near which time he made the promiſe in <hi>Matthew</hi>) <hi>he gave ſome Apostles; and ſome prophets; and ſome Evangeliſts; and ſome paſtours and teachers; for the perfecting of the Saints, for the worke of the miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Christ.</hi> Thus our <hi>Engliſh</hi> reads it: But the <hi>Greeke bible</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Compluti,</hi> hath it thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>He gave ſome Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les, ſome prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome pastours and teachers for the perfecting of the Saints unto the worke of the miniſtry for the edifying of the body of Chriſt.</hi> So the Latine verſion there hath it— <hi>paſtores &amp;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170450:19"/>doctores ad conſummationem ſanctorum in opus ministerii in edificationem corporis Christi.</hi> Here is no <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> of <hi>Ministers,</hi> no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ordinary and extraordinary officers, ſome to build, others to lay the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangelists, paſtours and teachers,</hi> all are given [not to perpetuate in a <hi>ſucceſſion,</hi> but] <hi>to perfect the Saints for the worke of the ministry.</hi> The perſons to <hi>carry on</hi> the <hi>work</hi> are the <hi>ſaints</hi> perfected for it, and the end of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry is the <hi>building up of the body of Christ.</hi> Judge now, Sir, how Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is out in his <hi>Greeke,</hi> who from <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. ſaith, <q>
                  <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and teachers</hi> [are given to the Church] <hi>for the perfecting of the ſaints, for the worke of the miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Christ</hi> &amp;c. Extraordinary and ordinary officers are here conjoyned, who between them are to perfect the building, the firſt laying the foundation,</q> and the latter building thereon. Theſe laſt words contain a <hi>diſtinction</hi> not recorded in Scripture, and it is an uſuall ſaying, <hi>non eſt diſtinguendum ubi lex non diſtinguit.</hi> None ought to diſtinguiſh where the law (eſpecially <hi>God's law</hi>) is ſilent. Oh! that Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> would prove <hi>paſtours</hi> and <hi>teachers</hi> to be <hi>diſtinct:</hi> or that the <hi>latter</hi> together with <hi>prophets</hi> (whatſoever become of <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts</hi>) were any way <hi>Officers:</hi> or, that we are to <hi>recede</hi> from a <hi>literall</hi> ſenſe to a <hi>figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative</hi> one, when there is no neceſſity; yet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170450:20"/>it is obſerved by <hi>Grotius</hi> upon the place, that here is a <hi>Trajection,</hi> the <hi>immediate end</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing given, was the <hi>work of the miniſtry.</hi> But not onely doth the <hi>literall placing</hi> favour me, but alſo the <hi>conſtruction</hi> of the words in <hi>Greeke</hi> that <hi>change,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of <hi>prepoſitions</hi> [eſpecially the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Syntaxe of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> being with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] cannot be inſignificant. The <hi>text</hi> as I have repreſented it, and expounded it, agrees with the <hi>beſt manuſcripts,</hi> with the <hi>Bohemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Daniſh, German, Polinian</hi> Verſions. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Teſtament hath it, <hi>for the conſummation of the Saints in the work of the Miniſtery,</hi> &amp;c. (ſee <hi>Elias Hutterus</hi>) In ſumme, the very <hi>vulgar edition</hi> of Pope <hi>ſixtus</hi> reads it no otherwiſe: And he muſt have no skill in <hi>Greeke</hi> that admits it not, ſince <hi>all peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods, commas, parentheſes, accents, diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into chapter and verſe,</hi> all theſe are <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell</hi> and of <hi>no authority.</hi> You may now give me, leave to diſmiſs Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> from his <hi>Greeke</hi> examen, I hope I have not been <hi>tedious</hi> though <hi>long;</hi> and that the effect of theſe laſt <hi>digreſſions</hi> will be more then an <hi>uſe of humility</hi> to Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> For his <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> as to the <hi>compoſure</hi> thereof, if one of the <hi>Articles</hi> for condemning <hi>John Huſſe</hi> the <hi>Martyr</hi> to the fire, was that he wrote <hi>falſe Latine,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> would not have eſcaped at the <hi>Councill</hi> of <hi>Constance.</hi> There is a marginall account of his maladies in <hi>Latine</hi> p. 90. <hi>Poſtea autem affectione Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandriacâ
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170450:20"/>innumerabilibus forè stipatâ ſymptomatibus pèr annos</hi> 14 <hi>laborâſſet, in longam tandem &amp; inexpugnabilem inciderit debilitatem &amp; contabeſcentiam, &amp; demum in narium haemorrhagiam ad l.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; inde in Atrophiam, pro deplorato a medicis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiſſimis relictus est: in quâ tamen Atrophiâ ex immenſâ Dei bonitate debilis ad huc ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivit: modis etiam poſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mirabilibus ex orci favibus ſaepiùs ereptus.</hi> If I had a better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the <hi>state of his body,</hi> I ſhould, I think, as much <hi>laugh</hi> at the <hi>miraculous</hi> reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of his <hi>infirmities,</hi> as I now do at his <hi>Latine elegancies:</hi> my preſent thoughts are, that if he underſtood [by all his <hi>phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,</hi> and <hi>phyſick</hi>] the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>blood,</hi> and <hi>life</hi> of man, and had conſidered the ſtory of the man <hi>in Oeneadis</hi> Hippocr. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. 5. §. 6. his <hi>cure</hi> would have ſeemed leſſe <hi>miraculous,</hi> and <hi>Phyſicians more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</hi> But ſome may ſay, that one who cannot <hi>write Latine</hi> may <hi>understand</hi> it, and ſo he may be <hi>ſufficiently</hi> qualified for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of <hi>learning,</hi> if he have but ſo much as will enable to apprehend others: he quotes Latine Authors, <hi>Fathers, Councils</hi> and <hi>Schoole-men</hi> in abundance. There are not wanting thoſe that will ſay he hath not <hi>capacity</hi> enough to <hi>understand</hi> the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter [and I would evince it in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, but I will reſerve ſeverall things till a further occaſion, when I may either have <hi>time</hi> to read over his works, or the <hi>publick
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170450:21"/>concerns</hi> may require it though I grant him knowledge enough for that purpoſe, as farre as a <hi>ſmall skill in Latine</hi> will advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage him, and a <hi>very ſmall skill</hi> is ſufficient for that deſign: But that any man ſhould think without a <hi>profound knowledge</hi> in <hi>Greeke,</hi> and <hi>I atine</hi> to determine of <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, affaires of the Church,</hi> or to be able to underſtand the <hi>primitive Fathers,</hi> is to me the <hi>greateſt folly</hi> that an <hi>Hypochondri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack</hi> can be poſſeſſed withall. That ſingle controverſie of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is of ſuch difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and requires ſo much of this <hi>learning</hi> an conve rſe with an infinity of <hi>Greeke</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, (the verſions of which are very bad) that I pitty Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> if any ſolid <hi>Epiſcoparian</hi> ſhall <hi>daign</hi> to make him his adverſary.</p>
            <p>Though the inſertion here be unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, yet give me leave to tell Mr. Br. that it was ignorantly ſaid of him in his <hi>ſecond ſheet for the ministry,</hi> p. 12. ſhat the <q>
                  <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers had no being in the World till a few years agoe.</hi>
               </q> If he means as to the name, I grant it; but ſo had not the <hi>protestants;</hi> as he admitteth of: but if as to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of their opinions and deporment, I DOE A VOW it out of as ſure and good records as any can be produced, that they can plead more for themſelves from the firſt 270. years, then Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Orthodox religion</hi> laid down in the <hi>Saints ever lasting rest,</hi> or the <hi>confeſſion of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170450:21"/>the Aſſembly.</hi> It is falſe that he ſaith, the <hi>Puritans</hi> were <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> It is falſe that he ſaith the <hi>Protestants</hi> allow not of <hi>wars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Magiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates,</hi> and <hi>of depoſing them:</hi> let the practices of <hi>France, Geneva, Savoy, Holland, Germany, Swedeland, Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland</hi> be examined. It is a <hi>baſe belying</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Papists</hi> to charge them with <hi>diſloyall doctranes</hi> in generall: They have written better againſt the <hi>Pope's power in temporal's</hi> then Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> They do not own his infallibility, nor will they grant him any power to <hi>deprive Kings of their Kangdoms,</hi> and civill ſubjection by encommunication. They hate the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> (and many <hi>noble families</hi> will not admit them <hi>within their doores</hi>) and revere the memory of <hi>Widdrington, Preſton,</hi> &amp;c. as much as they deteſt <hi>Parſons,</hi> and <hi>Garnets</hi> actings. Their Remonſtrances to Q. Eliz. their ſubjection to K. Edw. 6. K. <hi>James,</hi> and the teſtimonies they gave in the late wars, beſides the tranſactions under a <hi>Proteſtant King</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> abate the Vniverſality of a charge, whereof the <hi>Spanyards, Jeſuites</hi> and Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>party of <hi>Italy</hi> are onely guilty. Theſe things may ſatisfie you, or any elſe, of Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> great abilities in ſeverall ſtudies, of an whereof the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaid, <hi>who is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fierent for it!</hi> To conclude his <hi>Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies</hi> he is of late turned <hi>State-Tinker,</hi> and demeanes himſelf in <hi>politiques</hi> as ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170450:22"/>
               <hi>as in other matters.</hi> Oh! what pitty it is I cannot write him Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> of <hi>Banbury,</hi> as well as <hi>Kederminſter!</hi> I know not whoſe <hi>penſioner</hi> he is of late become; but any man may ſee whoſe <hi>projects</hi> he venteth: if he be not bribed, I am told he hath been <hi>cajolled,</hi> and careſſed with complements and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents into an eſteem for a compliance with them whom he ought to deteſt no leſſe then others. Poſſibly this is not true; and poſſibly our <hi>young-ſtates-man</hi> may be ſuch a novice as to be inſenſibly drawn in by <hi>Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>artifices.</hi> In his addreſſe to his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> before his <hi>Key, &amp;c.</hi> He deſires that he <q>would <hi>fruſtrate the ſubtility</hi> of the <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craticall politicians that are buſy about the change of Government, and would bring all into confuſion under the pretenſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's liberty or power, and would have the major part of the Subjects to be the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of the rest, that is the worſt, that are ſtill the most; and the ignorant, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rule themſelves; and the vitious, that are enemies and hinderers of piety; and the worldlings, that mind nothing but what is under their feet, and have no time to think on Heaven, they have ſo much to doe on Earth; as Auguſtine ſaith, had rather their were one Star leſſe in Heaven, then one cowe leſſe in their paſtures:</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>theſe muſt be our</hi> SOVERAIGNES. If <hi>Politicians</hi> be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by him in an evill ſenſe, it ſeems Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> hath no great quarrell with them, ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170450:22"/>they be not <hi>Democraticall:</hi> according to what is uſually obſerved, if one fawn upon the <hi>Clergy</hi> though he be as perfidious in all his actings as the moſt proflicate politique, yet ſhall he poſſeſſe their regards: But for a <hi>Democraticall politician,</hi> I underſtand not the name, if it be a co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umely; for to ſeeke the publick good, to decry and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert all ſelf-intereſted deſignes, to continue all power in the hand of the people, have ſo little of particular advantages in them, that it is not for corrupt policy to embrace that party <hi>Aristotle</hi> tells us that they who are ruled by the arbitrary commands of men (and all governments are ſuch where the <hi>Magistrate</hi> is no otherwiſe bound by law, then that he is judge of his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viations) are governed by beaſts; but they who are governed by laws are ruled by <hi>God. They are buſy to change the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment!</hi> are not the <hi>Baxterians</hi> ſo too? Is there any for the preſent modell of affaires? But Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> miſtakes; they would preſerve the Government, and the <hi>Monarchiall poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians</hi> would change it; they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue that liberty wherein the long <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> enſtated us; and to perfect a fabrick, is not to alter it: it is one thing to be <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour,</hi> and another to be <hi>Soveraigne</hi> of a <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> They <hi>would bring all things unto confuſion!</hi> becauſe they would bring all things to a <hi>ſettlement,</hi> and fix the <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> (as farre as prudence permits) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170450:23"/>a poſſibility of removal: they would ſecure the laws and immunities, the the ſpirituall and civill enjoyments of the good people of this land, and that unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyably: yet with Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> theſe are but pretenſes! ſhadows! not worth the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for! However all change is not to be condemned, but ſuch as is for the worſt; nor all confuſion, if the iſſue thereof be the publick ſafety. Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> is a practitioner in phyſick; poyſons and wholeſome medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, both alter the body, both create a confuſion in the humours, yet doth the one deſtroy, and the other Save. But they would have the Major part to be Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of the reſt. If ſo, then not Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, as he afterwards ſayes: you may ſee how much he hath thought on what he ſayes, who in ſo few lines cannot onely ſpeak non-ſenſe, but contradict himſelf. In a Democracy neither all, nor the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of the people are Soveraignes, but that Soveraignty which one <hi>Monarch</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes, the people ſhare by actuall exerciſe of their naturall right: Nor is any mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a well-formed common-wealth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by any majority to which he hath not previouſly conſented, or in the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which he hath not demeaned himſelf with as much prudence, as they who plow and ſowe not fearing a deluge or drought. It is falſe that the moſt are ſtill the worſt, and ignoranteſt: Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> that is accounted,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170450:23"/>probable which ſeems ſo to the moſt: and Ariſtotle ſaith, that the multitude, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) judgeth better then any one man whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: The multitude too is not ſo bad as Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> thinks: ſuch vices as render men unfit for ſtate employments are the debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries of a few, and not of a multitude, unleſſe that multitude be under one. I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet read of a <hi>Monarchy</hi> which did not in it's own tendency corrupt the beſt men; nor can I imagine a regulated Democracy, upon a ballance, ballot, and rotation of Governours which will not amend the worſt of men: Wickedneſs and Ignorance univerſal are the conſequences of <hi>Monarchy;</hi> they who plead that all may be free, and capable of bearing ſuch offices as they can merit, it is their intereſt as well as intent all ſhould deſerve. Theſe trifling argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> will not perſwade the ſtate of <hi>Venice, Holland, Switzerland, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi> the <hi>Hanſe-townes</hi> out of their liberty, nor overthrow the reall happineſſe <hi>Rome, Athens, Sparta, Syracuſe,</hi> &amp;c. enjoyed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that form of Government. I am ſorry Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> did not live in the time of <hi>Caligula,</hi> he who brought his horſe into the <hi>Senate,</hi> would have allowed Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> a place in his Cabinet, where he might have argued about the conveniency of a change of the principality of <hi>Rome</hi> into a <hi>Kingdom.</hi> God Almighty eſtabliſhed a Common-weal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſtiffe-necked <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> Chriſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170450:24"/>endowed his Church therewith; yea the name thereof, and others therein uſed are taken from this popular Government. Was not <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> then faithfull to him that apointed him? was not <hi>Moſes faithfull in all his houſe?</hi> Or are not theſe things written for our inſtruction, who are ſo farre from being incapable of a Democracy, that we are not capable of a <hi>Monarchy.</hi> (It is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ignorant, and unexperienced to commend a <hi>Linſey-woolſey mixt-Monarchy:</hi> nor is it for a Chriſtian here to practiſe an abſolute one) I would this puny ſtatiſt had ſhewed his Highneſs how he muſt have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched the Gentry out of their eſtates, and advanced a Nobility to ſuch riches and eſteem, as that their power might over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance the Commons; (without which there is no ſecurity) or that he had divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the land unto <hi>Timariots,</hi> and ſo erected a <hi>Monarchy</hi> upon a military intereſt: or ſhewed a third way of ſettlement. But I leave this cauſe to be managed by better pennes, though I may remit Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> to the Lord <hi>Broghill,</hi> who in his <hi>Partheniſſa</hi> hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently debated the caſe of a Republick, let them give, or receive ſatisfaction one of another. As for Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi> there is too much of learning and judgment in his works that I ſhould referre Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> thereunto: his modell is ſo farre above the praiſes, as it agrees with the poſture of our Nation.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170450:24"/>
            <p>Sr. I ſhould entertain you with more raillery about Mr. <hi>Br's.</hi> Catholiciſme (that is a <hi>Greeke</hi> word, but not the onely one which he makes uſe of though he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them not) and with his deſignes for peace, in which there is nothing almoſt good but the deſignes themſelves. But I ſhall no longer detain you from reading a vindication of the truly Honourable Sr. <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> which was the principall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (next to the concerns of the publick) that induced me to this writing. You may from what I have already ſaid frame a character of this Retailer of other mens reading, and Quoter of quotatations? Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> his abilities, and diſcretion; the latter cannot be ſo little, but the former is leſſe; and if you will any way uphold his credit, it muſt be by ſuch a diſtinction as whereby <hi>Strafford</hi> loſt his <hi>Head;</hi> though the parts of his accuſation were not treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, yet put together they did amount to Accumulative Treaſon, ſo Mr. Br. may own an accumulative learning though he be deficient in all manner of knowledg.</p>
            <p>Had this Honourable and pious <hi>Knight</hi> had any other name, Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> had loſt ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall jeaſts and clinches, which I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to preſerve to poſterity, that they may know the man had ſome wit though no learning. In the dedication to his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> he calls ſuch as adhere to Sr. H. <hi>Vane</hi> the <hi>Vani.</hi> and p. 342. <q>The <hi>Vane</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170450:25"/>and <hi>Steril</hi> language of <hi>Paracelſian Behme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> and popiſh juglers doth ſerve me for no other uſe but to raiſe me into ſuſpicion of their deſignes and doctrines, and to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a <hi>Vaine</hi> and <hi>Steril</hi> minde.</q> I am heartily ſorry (out of compaſſion to the new edition of <hi>Archy,</hi> the Court-fool, his jeaſts) that for Sr. <hi>Henry</hi> his adverſaries name was not Sr. <hi>Walter;</hi> and a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie was not agitated, whether the Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name were <hi>FANE</hi> or <hi>VANE,</hi> then we ſhould not have been put to repetition for want of freſh wit, but out of phyſick we might have heard of the <hi>Tela Gualiteri;</hi> I am <hi>Scandit Gualter</hi> had not been loſt; nor would Mr. <hi>Br's</hi> perſecuting ſpirit (I am informed that he ſtrook a <hi>Quaker</hi> openly) have omitted the raillery of an Halter. We ſhould have heard of fictions too (as now of Hiding) and a Grammaticall diſpute might have been moved, whether the new <hi>Cavaliers</hi> ſhould not be called the <hi>profane, profani tanquam procul a fano,</hi> as being oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites to the <hi>Fanes:</hi> you will pardon me if I took notice of this <hi>Kedenminster wit; it</hi> is remarkable in regard both of the Vanity and Sterility of the man, that neither Malice (which uſually ſupplies naturall deficiencies in point of wit) nor Melancholy (which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> obſerveth to diſpoſe men to ingenuity) ſhould not furniſh him with better Quibbles; yet they are as good as what he objecteth in earneſt againſt the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170450:25"/>
               <hi>Patriot.</hi> So certain it is that we can do nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth. He very often reflects upon him under the term of an <hi>Hider.</hi> I do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his reaſon for it; fince Sr. <hi>H. V.</hi> hath never declined to give forth an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that hope that is in him. He ſpeaks plain and good Engliſh, and if in his words the ſpirituality of the matter make all ſeeme to be hidden, it is but the fate of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſoul-ſaving truths, that they are hid to them that periſh: the <hi>Calumny</hi> of Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> is very old, and made uſe of by the old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in the <hi>Apostles</hi> time: but they having renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, gave this reaſon of their hidden words. <hi>If our goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt: in whom the God of this World hath blinded the minds of them that believe not, least the light of the glorious goſpell of Chriſt, who is the image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them.</hi> 2. Cor. 4. v. 3.4. But what reaſon is there Sr. <hi>H.</hi> ſhould ſuffer for Mr. <hi>Br's</hi> intellectualls? thouſands bear witneſſe to the pretionſneſſe of thoſe truths, they are his ſeale, and experiment the comfort of what Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> condemnes as vain and empty. This will be of no ſtrength till our great phyſician avow that we ought to reſign up our ſenſes to the deluſions of <hi>Hypochondriaques;</hi> and becauſe the ſtupid do not, we muſt not ſay we do feel. What if <hi>Paul</hi> be reputed a babler by the <hi>Grecians</hi> (as Sr. <hi>H.</hi> is by one that is no <hi>Grecian</hi>)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170450:26"/>what if the doctrine of ſaving grace be a ſtumbling-block to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and folly to the <hi>Greekes?</hi> muſt the ſaints therefore quit their hopes of Salvation, and that which is to them a Savour of life unto life? We know what it is that the animall man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaineth not, becauſe it is fooliſhneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, neither can he, becauſe it is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to be diſcerned: But ſhall the man of God be concluded by thoſe his ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he ſhould thereupon renounce him, who is made unto us wiſdome, and ſanctification? ſhall the enlightned com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of Darkneſs, becauſe to others the light ſhineth in darkneſſe, and the darkneſs comprehendeth it not? If Sr. <hi>H. Vane</hi> had opened his mouth in parables, how ſhould he have been called an <hi>Hider?</hi> And may not Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> be called an <hi>Hider,</hi> that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcures the light of the Goſpell by intricate diſputes? is there any thing more hid then the Aphoriſmes, which if no man ſhould be juſtified but who underſtand them upon Mr. <hi>Brs.</hi> propoſal, the redeemed of the Lord will make up a leſſe flock, then is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived? Might not he alſo be called an <hi>Hider,</hi> becauſe under a pretended zeal he hides the malice of others in his ſlaunderous books.</p>
            <p>He tells his Highneſſe in the dedication that the <q>
                  <hi>Vani</hi> have been confounded by God by wonders in New England, but have here prevailed farre in the dark.</q> As for their prevailing in the Dark, I am not acquainted therewith. I am ſure Sr. H.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170450:26"/>never hid his candle under a buſhell; what he hath taught, he hath done it openly, before great Auditories, and as great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages for ſpirituall diſcernings as this nation affordes. He may almoſt reply in <hi>Chriſt's</hi> words, <hi>I ſat daily with you teaching in the Temple, and ye laid no hold of me.</hi> But ſuppoſe the <hi>Vani</hi> had encreaſed in the darke: ought that to prejudice a good caſe? Or is it not a reflection upon the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of ſuch Governours as forced truth into corners. Truth and errour may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in the darke, but the former brings a light to diſpell darkneſs, which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther augmenteth, or doth onely vary.</p>
            <p>As for the wonders wherewith, God hath witneſſed againſt them in <hi>New England I</hi> am a ſtranger to the tranſactions of that land; yet I may very well ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> hath not omitted any thing that might tend to their diſrepute in that digreſſion which he on purpoſe framed againſt them. p. 330. The principall of theſe <hi>Hiders</hi> are <q>the <hi>Vani,</hi> whoſe game was firſt played o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in <hi>America</hi> in <hi>New England,</hi> where God gave in his teſtimony againſt them from Heaven upon their two propheteſſes, Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Dyer:</hi> the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brought forth a monſter with the parts of a bird, beaſt, fiſh, and man, which you may ſee deſcribed in Mr. <hi>Welds's</hi> narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, with their diſcovery, the concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and conſequents. The former brought forth many (near 30) monſtrous births
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170450:27"/>at once, and was after ſlain by the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> This providence ſhould at leaſt have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakned England to ſuch a Godly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, as to have better tryed the doctrines which God thus ſeemed to caſt out, before they had ſo greedily entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, as in part of <hi>Lincolne-ſhire, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg-ſhire,</hi> and many other parts they have done. At leaſt it ſhould have wakened the Parliament to a wiſe and godly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly of the councels and deſignes of him that was in <hi>New England</hi> the maſter of the game, and to have carefully ſearched how much of his doctrine and deſign were from Heaven, how much of them he brought with him from <hi>Italy,</hi> or at leaſt was begotten by the progenitour of monſters. Such extraordinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences ought not to be deſpiſed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I am not in a place where I can either informe my ſelf of thoſe accidents in <hi>New England,</hi> and how farre what Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> ſaith out of Mr. <hi>Weld's</hi> is true: nor can I meet with Mr. <hi>Weld's</hi> narrative that I might ſee whither Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> do more truly vouch him, then the word of God, or <hi>Greek</hi> writers: <hi>I</hi> would therefore grant his <hi>Aſſertions,</hi> did not that paſſage of Sr. <hi>H. Vane's</hi> bringing his doctrines with him out of <hi>Italy</hi> (where he never was) make me tender of crediting all Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> ſayes.
<note place="margin">I have ſince the writing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſpoken with Mr. <hi>Clerke</hi> of <hi>New England,</hi> who was there at the time of theſe monſtrous births. As for Mrs. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yer</hi> he could not ſay any thing of his own knowledg, but that ſhe was privatly delivered, two wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men onely being by, of a falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth, which was buryed imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately: and from theſe <hi>two women</hi> comes this <hi>Narrative:</hi> for though it was digged up eight days after, yet the ſhape was not determinable. He was at Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> when ſhe was delivered of what he had <hi>long foretol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> would be a <hi>Mola:</hi> it was a miſhapen beaſt, which being ſeparated from its <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ates</hi> and integuments, did put into <hi>four</hi> pieces, <hi>two</hi> were like clotted blood in a tunicle, and <hi>two</hi> like cluſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of grapes, bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>congeries</hi> of litle <hi>round bladders</hi> full of water onely. This he was an eye witneſs of; and Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> having related openly ſuch ſtories as Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> doth, did in the open Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation at <hi>Boſton</hi> retract them, as I expect Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> should do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or prove each veſicula of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be a <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſter.</hi>
               </note> The name of propheteſſes is made uſe of by way of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170450:27"/>reproach (I ſuppoſe) God forgive him! <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> was not againſt <hi>women's</hi> prophecying; nor <hi>God,</hi> who, beſides inſtances in the <hi>old,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>new teſtament</hi> endowed <hi>Philip's</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with prophecying; and <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith Act. 2. v. 16.17.18. <hi>This is that which was ſpoken by the prophet Joel, And it ſhall come to paſſe in the laſt dayes, (ſaith God) I will poure out of my ſpirit upon all fleſh, and your ſonnes and your DA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERS ſhall propheſy, and your young</hi> men <hi>ſhall ſee viſions, and your old men ſhall dream dreams: and on my ſervants, and on my HANDMAIDENS, I will poure out in thoſe days of my ſpirit, and they ſhall propheſy.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> liketh not this diſpenſation of the ſpirit; the Holy <hi>Ghoſt</hi> though it be given to every one to profit with [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] yee women muſt be excepted untill Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> learn <hi>Greeke.</hi> It is obſervable that Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> in the <hi>body of his booke</hi> ſpeakes <hi>timorouſly,</hi> as if his Objection from the providentiall actings of God were of no great moment. Theſe things
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170450:28"/>ſhould have awakened at leaſt England to ſuch a godly jealouſie as to have better tryed the doctrines which God thus ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to caſt out, before they ſo greedily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained them.— I am confident S. H. V. never deſired any man to embrace his doctrine without trying it: the example of the <hi>Beraeans</hi> doth not offend him: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured of the truthes he layes down, that they will abide in the <hi>day of the Lord,</hi> he feares not <hi>man's day.</hi> Yet he conceives that the precept to trye all things, doth not exclude the holding faſt [or laying faſt hold on] that which is good. To ſuch enquiries he wiſhes all men were inclined, and that not upon the motives Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> layes down, but upon the accompt of <hi>ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concernes.</hi> As for <hi>Godly jealouſy,</hi> I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not the term; I ſee Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>Zaphnath Pahaneach</hi> (as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> named <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Gen. 41. v. 45.) or a <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverer of what is Hidden;</hi> he is now got amongſt the <hi>Hiders;</hi> and indeed it is no commendation for him to <hi>Hide Malice.</hi> Godly jealouſie is of a deſtroying nature: <hi>Phinehas</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Eleazer</hi> when he ſlew <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi</hi> is ſaid to have had a <hi>Godly jealouſie,</hi> Num. 25. v. 11.13. <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie</hi> for God being all one, both there and elſewhere. How farre then this <hi>Godly jealouſie</hi> ſhould have extended, Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> limits not: nor yet that <hi>wiſe and godly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie in the Parliament,</hi> which Sr. <hi>H. Vane</hi> is ſo farre from dreading, that he would
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170450:28"/>joyne (I dare ſay) with Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> in the advice: he ownes no doctrine nor deſignes but ſuch as <hi>Heaven inſpires</hi> him with, and which he will not be aſhamed of on earth, leaſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be <hi>aſhamed of him before his father.</hi> If he had been in <hi>Italy</hi> he would have brought thence no other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, no other <hi>faith</hi> then what <hi>Paul</hi> plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there, and of which he telleth the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that their <hi>faith was ſpoken of over the whole earth.</hi> Yet is not Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> ſo mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate here as he might have been, for if God did but <hi>Seeme to cast out the Vaniſts,</hi> how comes he to ſay that <hi>God hath given in his testimony againſt them from Heaven upon their two propheteſſes.</hi> Who taught Mr. <hi>B.</hi> to make poſitive concluſions from ſeeming premiſes? Thus he told the Protectour, that <hi>God had confounded them by wonders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is but a remote argument drawn from the providentiall actings of God in and upon two perſons that witneſſed ſome of thoſe truths (though with ſeverall weakneſſes) unto which Sr. <hi>H. Vane</hi> hath given out a teſtimony amongſt us. There are ſome that cry up Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> for a rationall diſputant, unleſſe he have given them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evidence then I ſee, it muſt be for ſome hidden excellencies. I know not how he came to be of God's counſell, and to underſtand the intent of his various diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations. He was a wiſe man (without diſparagement to Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> be it ſpoken) who ſaid Eccleſ. 9. <hi>v.</hi> 1. 2. 3. <hi>All this I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170450:29"/>in my heart, even to declare all this, that the righteous and the wiſe and their workes are in the hand of God: no man knoweth</hi> [except Mr. <hi>B.] love or hatred by all that is before them. All things come alike to all, there is one event to the righteous and to the wicked, to the good and to the clean:</hi> it is a very unſafe way then to argue from events to the juſtice of a cauſe, or it's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, for thoſe things Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> urgeth, (though it be not neceſſary that <hi>Monſters</hi> ſhould be ominous, as <hi>Licetus</hi> and <hi>Riolanus</hi> obſerve) they may as well [unleſſe Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> hide a part of his evidence] have been warnings to the <hi>Colony</hi> or natives, as <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</hi> When a <hi>Sheep</hi> of old yeaned a <hi>Lyon,</hi> it was no ill-aboading preſage to the <hi>ſheep,</hi> but to the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> that ſhould fall under <hi>Tyranny.</hi> God often times takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the righteous, but in mercy, and out of judgment to the ſurviving wicked. The Eclipſe at Chriſt's death, the diſturbances and deſtruction enſuing in <hi>Judea,</hi> were no declarations againſt Chriſtianity: no more then the ſad ends to which many of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and other eminent Servants of God came, <hi>James</hi> was ſlain by the ſword, <hi>Paul</hi> ſcourged, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p-wracked at <hi>Melite,</hi> there a viper faſtened on his hand, and the people (like Mr. <hi>Br.</hi>) concluded, No <hi>doubt this man is a murtherer, whom though he hath eſcaped at ſea, yet vengeance ſuffereth not to live.</hi> The Calamities that befell the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire upon the preaching of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170450:29"/>the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> if Mr. <hi>Brs.</hi> arguing hold good, (contrary to <hi>Tertullian</hi>) were by them juſtly attributed to the Gods atteſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtians. <hi>The new Starre,</hi> the <hi>comet</hi> at the beginning of the reformation, was differently expounded by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Protestants.</hi> At <hi>Charenton</hi> (not many years agoe) there was a boate caſt away on the Lords day full of <hi>French Gentry</hi> and others, [either coming from, or going to Church] which the <hi>Papists</hi> avowed for a judgment; but <hi>Mounſieur Daille</hi> in a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon about thoſe on whom the tower <hi>Silo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> fell, refuted thoſe conjectures. As they upon whom the tower of <hi>Siloam</hi> did fall, and they whoſe blood <hi>Pilate</hi> mingled with their ſacrifices, were not greater ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners then others; but ſuffer'd for example, that all might repent: ſo I hope Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> will acquit O. P, from an ominous diſſolution; that day being famous for the vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one, and death of another uſurper.</p>
            <p>But might not one ſay, that the prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous birth of Mrs. <hi>Dier's,</hi> was a witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the polity of thoſe days in it's ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral corruptions: men deſiring then <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> though of perſons as <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> as was her <hi>monſter?</hi> Or, might it not be an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem</hi> of the various temptations, thorough the influence whereof they who either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs are inſtigated; and ſuch are the ſpoiles of birds, beaſts, and fiſhes, wherewith man ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>prideth</hi> or <hi>pampereth</hi> himſelf. It is <hi>an
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170450:30"/>adulterous generation that asketh a ſigne;</hi> and it is none of the wiſeſt that judgeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.
<note place="margin">Her death is to be laid at the doores of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m that perſecute her, ſo as that to avoid the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y affrighted her with, flee fled, and was ſlain by the Indians as they ſet upon the Dutch planters.</note> As for Mrs. <hi>Hutchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's</hi> being ſlain by the <hi>Indians,</hi> Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> ought to know, that <hi>there is a juſt man that periſheth in his righteouſneſs, and there is a wicked man that prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his life in Wickedneſs.</hi> Eccleſ. 7.15. <hi>There be juſt men to whom it happeneth according to the worke of the wicked: again there be wicked men, to whom it happeneth according to the worke of the righteous:</hi> And if <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſay that <hi>this is vanity</hi> (Eccleſ. 8. v. 14.) I may ſay ſo of Mr. <hi>Brs.</hi> arguing I am ſure: I could enter upon a diſcourſe about the <hi>cauſe of Monsters,</hi> but that what I have ſaid is enough to chaſtiſe Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> for his <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory cenſure,</hi> which (though twice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated) hath little of the two-edged ſword, but much of an edged picture, which according to the different Station of the beholder entertaines him with a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent repreſentation. If one ſhould ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue againſt Mr. <hi>Brs.</hi> opinions, that an evill diſeaſe cleaveth unto the <hi>Authour,</hi> that God hath declared againſt his tenets by the ſad afflictions which he hath layed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no him, that he hath viſited him in wrath, and chaſtiſed him in his ſore diſpleaſure: that by <hi>Hypochondriacall</hi> diſtempers he hath witneſſed againſt the flatulency of his brain; that by the maladies of his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170450:30"/>ſpleen, and rivers of blood iſſuing from his noſe, he doth wonderouſly confound his malice, and ſanguinary principles. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia te ſanguine quem ſitiviſtr:</hi> that thoſe profuſions from the neighbouring parts warne him to employ his eyes in lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the troubles to which he contributes in this Nation; in fine, that the <hi>Atrophy of his body</hi> is a manifeſtation of the <hi>Sterility</hi> of his principles. Theſe diſcourſes have a ſhew of as much reaſon as Mr. <hi>Baxter's,</hi> and not leſſe ingenuity.</p>
            <p>
               <q>But Sr. <hi>Henry Vane</hi> is ſundry times by him called cloſe-papiſt; and ſuch are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that they may be kept out of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, Armies, Councills,</hi> &amp;c.</q> There is none that know the frame of Sr. <hi>Henry Vane's</hi> ſpirit, but can bear me witneſſe, that if the cauſe of God, and the good of his people amongſt us, did not prevaile mightily upon him, and the apprehenſions thereof as it were eat Him up, he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enjoy a retiredneſſe under the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate teachings of God's ſpirit, then be taken up with diſtracting employments in <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Councills.</hi> This would be to him an infinite ſatisfaction, (and to be valued above all thoſe preferments, and dignities, which he as much deſerves, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers can ambition them) to ſpend his time in <hi>ſoule-converſes with his beloved,</hi> and thoſe delights which attend the higheſt ſpirituall entertainments, that ſo much Meekneſs, Humility; and unfeigned piety
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170450:31"/>is capable of. As for his being a cloſe-pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, it is a <hi>calumny</hi> that nothing but a <hi>tongue ſet on fire by Hell</hi> (and not <hi>touched with a coale from the Altar</hi>) could utter: which the moſt bare-faced enemies of the publick good and tranquility of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the moſt ambitious and ſelf-ſeeking men (with whoſe intereſt Sr. <hi>H. Vane's</hi> uprightneſs doth enterfere) never yet charged him with. But Mr. <hi>Richard Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> may ſay any thing, either as tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Zeal (though not according to knowledg) or bribed, or enveigled into ſuch language. There is not a man in this Nation who hath more layed his Ax to the roote of Popery, then Sr. <hi>Henry Vane;</hi> no man hath ſo thoroughly endeavour'd to extinguiſh that Myſtery of iniquity, in which Mr. Baxter, (moderate and healing Mr. Baxter) ſaith he walkes. How farre Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> hath been wronged in the charges of <hi>Arminianiſm, Socinianiſme, Pelagianiſme,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> I ſhall not now diſcuſſe: certain I am that they who charged him therewith, had colourable pretenſes for thoſe imputations; and the very ſenſe hereof might have made him leſſe precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate to aſperſe others; but his earneſtneſſe for <hi>Bethel</hi> made him not apprehend thoughts of <hi>Sion.</hi> The Authour to the <hi>Hebrews, c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 17. ſaith, <hi>in all things it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooved Chriſt to be made like unto his brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, that he might be a mercifull and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full high-prieſt—for in that he himſelf hath
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170450:31"/>ſuffer'd being tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that be tempted.</hi> But though Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> hath had his ſhare in <hi>tongue-ſufferings,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>worſt quality,</hi> yet hath not that diſpoſed him to a <hi>tenderneſs</hi> towards others; and that which was ſo effectuall in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hath loſt it's prevalency upon this <hi>pſeudo-minister.</hi> If <hi>to destroy all Spirituall power that uſurpeth upon the rule and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Lord Jeſus, all ſoule-oppreſſion, and conſcience-diſtreſſing perſecution,</hi> be to <hi>be an Abettour of Rome, it's power, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition;</hi> If <hi>to cry grace, grace to the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and builders of Sion,</hi> be <hi>to comply with Babylon, and make one a partiſan of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ;</hi> Farewell <hi>all the declarations of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted innocency, and let not Chriſt</hi> [nor Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>] call for a <hi>confeſſion or profeſſion of faith, which though never ſo poſitive, evident and clear, cannot defend a man from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of</hi> CLOSE PAPIST. Are thoſe doctrines fetched from <hi>Bellarmine, Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Gretſer,</hi> which are as oppoſite to them, as to Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> deſignes; Did <hi>Sr. H. V.</hi> deveſt the civill <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> of ſpirituall power to inveſt the <hi>Pope</hi> therewith, Mr. <hi>Brs.</hi> words had not been groundleſſe, as now they are, ſince he no more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the <hi>Pope</hi> by ſuch his opinions, then the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> out of which number I do not yet here of any that think Sr. H. V. doth agitate cloſely their cauſe, and is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand an abettour of <hi>Presbytery.</hi> To deny the <hi>Civill Magiſtrate</hi> power of <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170450:32"/>in religion;</hi> for this he needed not have gone to <hi>Italy,</hi> nor conſult <hi>Bellarmine, Parſons</hi> or <hi>Gretſer</hi> (names made uſe of meerly to draw an <hi>odium</hi> upon him) The <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Presbyters in the <hi>Eraſtian</hi> and <hi>Vedelian</hi> controverſies would have furniſh'd Him with arguments; as Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> may have furniſhed himſelf from their <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagonists,</hi> or from <hi>Goldaſtus's</hi> collection of <hi>Popiſh</hi> writers, that defended the <hi>Emperour's</hi> authority againſt the <hi>Popes.</hi> You will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps reply, that what I have ſaid may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit Sr. <hi>H. V.</hi> from being an <hi>open papiſt,</hi> but not from being one <hi>in ſecret.</hi> Oh! ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed malice! againſt which there is <hi>no defence</hi> but an appeall to <hi>the ſearcher of hearts,</hi> ſince <hi>words</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> are not <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient fruits whereby to be known!</hi> Might not I ſay that Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> is a cloſe papiſt too? and give you the like anſwer when you ſhould alledge his frequent <hi>writings againſt them?</hi> Nay, could not I adde that <hi>many</hi> men may <hi>prevaricate</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith the <hi>Jefuites</hi> do amongſt <hi>our forces</hi>) and maintain what is not their judgment, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to create us new <hi>diviſions?</hi> and that the <hi>Romanists</hi> abound no where ſo much, as near Mr. <hi>Br?</hi> Might not I either, fix any <hi>odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous imputation</hi> upon Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> as <hi>Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Socinianiſme</hi> (upon another account then that <hi>his booke of infidelity</hi> is borrowed from <hi>Socinus</hi>) yea <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and ſay that he <hi>ownes all, or any of theſe,</hi> but <hi>cloſely.</hi> If this procedure be once admitted of, the <hi>whole
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170450:32"/>world</hi> muſt become <hi>criminall,</hi> and when <hi>ſurmiſes</hi> or <hi>bold aſſertions</hi> ſhall be taken for <hi>proofes</hi> none will be able to plead <hi>not-guilty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is not any thing more (that I know of) which Mr. <hi>Br.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr <hi>Rogers</hi> in his Vindication of Sir <hi>H. V.</hi> gives this full account of his having no hand in the Kings death: <q>That upon that great change and alteration of affairs in the year 1648, he abſented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the Parliament, and Lievtenant General <hi>Cronwell</hi> who ſat upon the Tryal of the King, and encouraged the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gh Court of Juſtice</hi> to ſentence h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>) could hardly, and after much importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, prevail w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h Sir <hi>H. V.</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume his place in <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Council of State:</hi> Now Mr <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>er</hi> (the matter of f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct being thus ſtated) if you would have been <hi>impartial,</hi> you ſhould rather have ſaid, That <hi>your Lord Protector</hi> and his followers had a chief hand in the death of the King (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon a publique or private account, I leave it to the Lord) then that Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> and the <hi>Vaniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> were the <hi>chief Actors</hi> in it: But you were reſolved to caſt dirt in the face of this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and ſo to ingratiate your ſelf with the <hi>New Court,</hi> the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whereof is now layd in the duſt, together with all <hi>your ſtat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Addreſſes.</hi>
                  </q>
               </note> hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to this Honorable perſonage, or reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with: for I do not eſteem my ſelf bound to take notice of that <hi>Satyr</hi> againſt thoſe <hi>Patriots of the long Parliament</hi> and Army, who <hi>executed ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> upon the <hi>late King,</hi> and erected a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> I have recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that part of his book to the <hi>ſouldiery,</hi> who if either their <hi>own repute,</hi> or the <hi>cauſe of God and of the good people of this land</hi> in their <hi>religious</hi> &amp; <hi>civil</hi> concernes be dear unto them, will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the language of the <hi>Pedant</hi> to be unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. If he had not been intereſted in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Vanists</hi> odious, how come they (who were none at all) to be more <hi>Regicides</hi> then the late <hi>Protector?</hi> If Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> were ſo <hi>impartial,</hi> as ſome would have him thought, why did he ſpare <hi>his memory,</hi> ſince many of thoſe things which are charged upon the <hi>Vanists Anabaptists,</hi> &amp;c. had their <hi>riſe</hi> and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170450:33"/>
               <hi>management</hi> principally <hi>from him,</hi> Some were onely his Acts. Did not he debauch the Army, if to engage them to the true ſervice of their countrey were to debauch them? was not he an enemy to <hi>Ministry</hi> and <hi>Tithes?</hi> did not he maintain and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a <hi>toleration?</hi> why then was not he upbraided with <hi>cloſe popery,</hi> &amp;c. If Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> is reſolved to meddle with no man, but ſuch whoſe names affoord him occaſion for a <hi>Quibble;</hi> he could not have miſſed of <hi>a Dozen</hi> in <hi>him,</hi> beſides that which is as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious from the <hi>Greeke</hi> as is that on Sr. <hi>H.</hi> from the <hi>Latin.</hi> Viz. that he endevoured to reduce us to our <hi>primitive ſlavery,</hi> to the <hi>onyons</hi> and garlick of <hi>Egypt:</hi> and that he would <hi>ſtink</hi> in the ſenſe of all poſterity: theſe had <hi>genuinely</hi> iſſued from the name of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>onyon.</hi> But I ſhall leave this diſcourſe to entertain you more ſeriouſly with an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into that invidious queſtion, which doth ſo much diſquiet Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> and others amongſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whither the civil Magiſtrate hath any thing to do in matters of ſpiritual concernment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon that ſubject I intend to ſet down what <hi>my own thoughts</hi> are, without inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſting any therein but <hi>my ſelf:</hi> being no leſſe reſolved <hi>alone</hi> to receive all that the <hi>Obloqui</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> of others can throwe upon me, then to continue all my life.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ch. Ch. <date>
                     <hi>April.</hi> 20. 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
               <signed>your moſt affectionate humble ſervant <hi>H. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
